

Uzmar de Jesús Gómez Yáñez

CURRICULUM VITAE

DATA SCIENTIST AT RACKSPACE TECHNOLOGY, BSC IN PHYSICS

PERSONAL STATEMENT

Learned to program throughout the Physics career, mainly in scientific computing topics. Hands-on experience applying Machine Learning algorithms to real business problems. Excellent usage of GNU / Linux systems and knowledge of object-oriented programming languages such as Python and C++. I have also worked in the academic field as a teacher assistant, teaching mathematics, computer science, physics and other topics at a university level. Good understanding of algorithms and data structures.

PERSONAL DATA

Address: Mexico City, Mexico Phone: +52 5539347885

EMAIL: uzmar.gomez@ciencias.unam.mx
LINKEDIN: www.linkedin.com/in/uzmargomez
GITHUB: https://github.com/uzmargomez

EDUCATION

PRESENT | MSc in Scientific Computing and Data Analysis, Department of Computer Science, Durham University,
Durham, United Kingdom.

Specialization: Earth and Environmental Sciences
OVERALL SCORE: - | Detailed List of Grades

2018 BSc in Physics, Faculty of Science, National Autonomous University of Mexico (UNAM), Mexico City,

2011 Thesis:

Thesis: "Numerical Study of Vlasov Equation in the Schwarzschild Metric"

Description: Creation of a finite differences scheme that evolves the relativistic Vlasov equation on a black hole metric background, assuming this is an advective equation, with velocities

dependent both on time and position.

Advisor: Dr. Miguel Alcubierre

OVERALL SCORE: 9.37/10 Detailed List of Grades

COMPUTER SKILLS

Programming Languages | Python, C/C++, Fortran, Julia, Go

Machine/Deep Learning | TensorFlow, Keras, PyTorch, Facebook Prophet, ARIMA, SARIMA, LDA, PCA,

Recommendation systems, Classification problems

Serving Seldon Core, TFServing Databases SQL, MongoDB Containers Docker, Kubernetes

Operating Systems | Debian GNU/Linux, Ubuntu GNU/Linux, Windows

Web Backend | Flask

Web Frontend | HTML, Bootstrap

Version Control | Gi

Parallel Computing
Data Visualization
Data Visualization
Data Visualization
Plotly Dash, Qlik, Tableau

GCP Tools (Console and CLI) | BigQuery, Compute Engine, Composer, Artifact Registry, Kubernetes Engine,

Storage, Data Studio, Kubeflow, Data Fusion, Cloud Build

LANGUAGES

ENGLISH: C1 Level - IELTS (2021)
SPANISH: Mothertongue

FRENCH: Basic

INTERESTS AND ACTIVITIES

Academic

Data Science, Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Numerical Analysis, General Relativity, Numerical Relativity, Black Holes.

Non academic

Science Fiction and Fantasy Reading, Running, Swimming, Playing the Guitar, Traveling, Videogames.

EXPERIENCE

Short Description

Jul 2020 - Present. Current job as a Data Scientist at Rackspace Technology. I helped on the migration of data from on-premises servers to the GCP cloud. I worked on a churn prediction model that uses features related to the COVID19 spreading aside from other business-related features to predict customer attrition, this work includes the development of the model using XGBoost, as well as the deployment of it using Kubeflow and the serving via Seldon Core. I'm also involved in constructing an SSAS OLAP Cube to be used by the company for inventory-related queries. I'm currently working on NLP tasks, such as the extraction of themes out of tickets using semantic similarity, by getting embeddings vectors out of sentences with a transformer architecture named Universal Sentence Encoder. I'm reading research on how to translate voice to text. I build two production-level applications using Plotly Dash.

Dec 2019 - Jun 2020. I worked on a face recognition system using a method called Sparse Representation and another one using Neural Networks. I acquired a deep understanding of Neural Networks for Face Detection and Recognition, Image Classification, Language Processing, among others, as well as some experience in Data Visualization tools such as Tableau.

Sep 2019 - Dec 2019. Data Scientist Trainee at Softtek. I learned about different statistical and machine learning techniques, as well as algorithms, to study a wide variety of problems.

2016 - 2019. As mentioned below, I have taught Computer Science classes, in which the Python programming language was introduced to Physics students.

Sep 2018 - Dec 2019. I have research experience using the Einstein Toolkit, a software platform created for supporting research in relativistic astrophysics and gravitational physics.

Subjects I have taught:

- · Computer Science.
 - https://web.fciencias.unam.mx/asignaturas/102.pdf
- Selected Topics in Relativity, Cosmology and Gravitation 1. https://web.fciencias.unam.mx/docencia/horarios/presentacion/295997
- Relativity
 - https://web.fciencias.unam.mx/asignaturas/718.pdf
- Mathematics I for Applied Sciences.
 - http://www.fciencias.unam.mx/asignaturas/1118.pdf
- Mathematics II for Applied Sciences.
 - http://www.fciencias.unam.mx/asignaturas/1216.pdf

Technical

Present	Data Scientist I at RACKSPACE TECHNOLOGY
JUL 2020	Mexico City, Mexico.
Jun 2020	Data Scientist at Softtek
DEC 2019	Mexico City, Mexico.
	·
DEC 2019	Data Scientist Trainee at SOFTTEK
SEP 2019	Mexico City, Mexico.

Vocational		
Semester 2019-2	Mexico City, Mexico.	MSa Alajandra Villarraal
	o Mathematics II for Applied Sciences	MSc. Alejandro Villarreal
Semester 2019-1	Teacher Assistant B at FACULTY OF SCIENCE, UNAM Mexico City, Mexico.	
	Selected Topics in Relativity, Cosmology and Gravitation IMathematics I for Applied Sciences	Dr. Miguel Alcubierre
Semester 2018-2	Teacher Assistant B at FACULTY OF SCIENCE, UNAM Mexico City, Mexico.	
	RelativityMathematics II for Applied Sciences	Dr. Miguel Alcubierre
Semester 2018-1	Teacher Assistant B at FACULTY OF SCIENCE, UNAM Mexico City, Mexico.	
	o Relativity	Dr. Miguel Alcubierre
	o Mathematics I for Applied Sciences	MSc. Alejandro Villarreal
Semester 2017-2	Teacher Assistant A at FACULTY OF SCIENCE, UNAM Mexico City, Mexico.	
	Mathematics II for Applied Sciences	MSc. Alejandro Villarreal
Semester 2017-1	Teacher Assistant A at FACULTY OF SCIENCE, UNAM Mexico City, Mexico.	
	o Mathematics I for Applied Sciences	MSc. Alejandro Villarreal
	o Computer Science	MSc. Alejandro Villarreal
Jun 2017	Teacher at Coordination of Programs of Differenti-	

ATED ATTENTION FOR STUDENTS, FACULTY OF ENGINEERING,

o Electrodynamics with an introduction to special relativity

Teacher Assistant A at FACULTY OF SCIENCE, UNAM

Eng. Raúl Puente

MSc. Alejandro Villarreal

CONFERENCES, COURSES, SCHOOLS AND WORKSHOPS ATTENDED

o Mathematics I for Applied Sciences

Computer Science Related

Semester 2016-1

UNAM

Mexico City, Mexico.

Mexico City, Mexico.

SEP 02, 2021 MAY 03, 2021	Course. Probability - The Science of Uncertainty and Data MITx on edX https://courses.edx.org/certificates/77ed32f3abc34158896ab5f2ee6d18be
OCT 09, 2020 OCT 08, 2020	Conference. THE Data Science Conference Online conference due to COVID19 https://www.thedatascienceconference.com
ОСТ 09, 2020 ОСТ 08, 2020	Course. Building Resilient Streaming Analytics Systems on GCP (COURSERA) Google Cloud Platform https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/ ZNG729Z9L78P
ОСТ 08, 2020 ОСТ 07, 2020	Course. Modernizing Data Lakes and Data Warehouses with GCP (COURSERA) Google Cloud Platform https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/ JUDDNMKRSBUA

OCT 07, 2020 SEP 10, 2020	Course. Building Batch Data Pipelines on GCP (COURSERA) Google Cloud Platform https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/ 8KTYPM3GZQS7
SEP 10, 2020 SEP 01, 2020	Course. Smart Analytics, Machine Learning, and AI on GCP (COURSERA) Google Cloud Platform https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/ LAZ8CNLM2M5A
AGO 09, 2020	Course. Google Cloud Platform Big Data and Machine Learning Fundamentals (COURSERA)
AGO 01, 2020	Google Cloud Platform https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/ S9HSH92LSALR
Jun 19, 2020 Jun 15, 2020	Course. Convolutional Neural Networks in TensorFlow (COURSERA) DeepLearning.ai
JUN 13, 2020	https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/76LGX8GCUG5D
Jun 15, 2020	Course . Introduction to TensorFlow for Artificial Intelligence, Machine Learning, and Deep Learning (COURSERA)
Jun 15, 2020	DeepLearning.ai https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/ LZJ2FSW2RJGP
MAY 04, 2020	Course. Al & Deep Learning with TensorFlow (EDUREKA)
MAR 04, 2020	Edureka! For Business https://www.edureka.co/lms/certificate/c3d0ebdc5518b429f6cc1a009454a9df
Mar 26, 2020 Ago 04, 2019	Specialization. Accelerated Computer Science Fundamentals (COURSERA) University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/specialization/
	certificate/DRF2CVM7P7FB
Mar 26, 2020	Course. Unordered Data Structures (COURSERA)
SEP 15, 2019	University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/ DFHE5FBHVAAD
Mar 04, 2020 Feb 10, 2020	Course. Python Statistics for Data Science Course (EDUREKA) Edureka! For Business
	https://www.edureka.co/lms/certificate/8a0976c4e21d5bee00ff053e2d8e3f3e
SEP 15, 2019 AGO 11, 2019	Course. Ordered Data Structures (COURSERA) University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign
, , ,	https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/ PZ9NABHA7XBY
Ago 11, 2019 Ago 04, 2019	Course. Object-Oriented Data Structures in C++ (COURSERA) University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign
AGO 04, 2019	https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/ 2YKURK8TJJ5B
Jul 29, 2019 Jun 02, 2019	Course. Algorithmic Toolbox (COURSERA) University of California San Diego, National Research University Higher School of Economics https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/FBZ5SK3E9BB6

APR 17, 2019 APR 03, 2019	Course. Operating Systems and You: Becoming a Power User (COURSERA) Grow with Google, Mexico City, Mexico. https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/ V6STDES4HLPE
Mar 10, 2019 Mar 08, 2019	Course. Python Data Structures (COURSERA) University of Michingan, Michigan, United States. https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/L6Y7MZQDAJHP
FEB 26, 2019 FEB 21, 2019	Course. Programming for Everybody (Getting Started with Python) (COURSERA) University of Michingan, Michigan, United States. https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/CNNYCJB5YB46
FEB 14, 2019 FEB 03, 2019	Course. Technical Support Fundamentals (COURSERA) Grow with Google, Mexico City, Mexico. https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/ YQRPQLC86CUM
FEB 5, 2019 FEB 3, 2019	Course. Introduction to Data Science: Statistical Programming with R (COURSERA) National Autonomous University of Mexico, Mexico City, Mexico. https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/E75DVAG2956T
Jun 13, 2018 Jun 9, 2018	School . <i>Deep Learning and Multimessenger Astronomy</i> Tecnológico de Monterrey, Guadalajara, Mexico.
Jan 27, 2017 Jan 16, 2017	Course. Basic Linux Faculty of Engineering UNAM, Mexico City, Mexico.
Jul 01, 2016 Jun 20, 2016	Course. Fortran Fundamentals Faculty of Engineering UNAM, Mexico City, Mexico.
Physics Related	!
Nov 11, 2018	School . Third Meeting of the Thematic Network of Black Holes and Gravitational Waves.
Nov 9, 2018	Playa del Carmen, Quintana Roo, Mexico.
Nov 9, 2018	School . Third School of Relativity and Gravitational Waves. XII School of the Division of Gravitation and Mathematical Physics.
Nov 5, 2018	Playa del Carmen, Quintana Roo, Mexico.
Aug 12, 2017 Aug 10, 2017	Workshop. Fifth Gravitation and Cosmology Workshop. Institute of Physical Sciences UNAM, Cuernavaca, Mexico.
Aug 9, 2017 Aug 7, 2017	School . Second School of Relativity and Gravitational Waves. Institute of Physical Sciences UNAM, Cuernavaca, Mexico.
Jan 18, 2016 Jan 7, 2016	Course. Introduction to Relativistic Electrodynamics Faculty of Engineering UNAM, Mexico City, Mexico.

VOLUNTEER ACTIVITIES

PRESENT Teacher
JUN 2021 Casa de la Sal

Support children with HIV on various Mathematics and English Language assignments.

SEP 2019 | Teacher

MAR 2019 University Student Council (CEU México)

Provide tools to university students to help develop their academic, professional and personal skills, to facilitate their employment and the definition of their life project.

MAR 2019 | Volunteer

SEP 2018 | Adopt a Talent Program (PAUTA)

Encourage scientific vocation so that those children and adolescents who like science and have outstanding skills, find a space where they can share their interest and learn from each other.

PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIP

SEP 2019 | Fellow

JAN 2017 Thematic Network of Black Holes and Gravitational Waves (Red ANyOG, CONACYT).

DEC 2019 | Student Associate

JAN 2016 Institute of Nuclear Sciences, UNAM.

JAN 2016 | Student Associate

JAN 2015 Institute of Physics, UNAM.

PRESENTATIONS AND POSTER SESSIONS

OCT 11, 2017 | Poster Presentation at LX NATIONAL CONGRESS OF PHYSICS.

Monterrey, Mexico

Presentation of a poster about my undergraduate thesis "Numerical Study of Vlasov

Equation in the Schwarzschild Metric".

SCHOLARSHIPS, AWARDS, HONORS AND ACCOMPLISHMENTS

2017 | Scholarship awarded for Conclusion of Proyect

2016 Support Program for Research Projects and Technological Innovation (PAPIIT).

2016 | Scholarship awarded for Conclusion of Undergraduate School

2015 Support Program for Research Projects and Technological Innovation (PAPIIT).

REFERENCES

NAME: Dr. Charles Mueller
OCCUPATION: Senior Engineer at Amazon

LINKEDIN: https://www.linkedin.com/in/charles-n-mueller/

NAME: Dr. Fernando Herrera

OCCUPATION: Senior Data Engineer at Revolut

LINKEDIN: https://www.linkedin.com/in/fernando-jose-herrera-elizalde-76a32790/

NAME: Dr. Miguel Alcubierre

INSTITUTION NAME: Institute of Nuclear Sciences, UNAM.

OCCUPATION: Director, Researcher, Teacher malcubi@nucleares.unam.mx

Master of Science in Scientific Computing and Data Analysis

Durham University Grades

Course	GRADE	CREDITS
Professional Skills		15
Project		60
Core la: Introduction to Machine Learning and Statistics		15
Core Ib: Introduction to Scientific and High-Performance Computing		15
Performance Engineering and Advanced Algorithms		15
Advanced Statistics and Machine Learning: Foundations and Unsupervised Learning		15
Advanced Statistics and Machine Learning: Regression and Classification		15
Earth and Environmental Sciences		30
	Total Credits	180
	OVERALL SCORE	-

Bachelor of Science in Physics

National Autonomous University of Mexico (UNAM) Grades

Course	Grade	CREDITS
Differential and Integral Calculus I	07	18
Algebra	10	10
Computer Science	10	6
Analytic Geometry I	08	10
Differential and Integral Calculus II	10	18
Contemporary Physics	09	6
Vector Mechanics	9	12
Analytic Geometry II	09	10
Mechanics Laboratory	10	6
Collective Phenomena	10	12
Collective Phenomena Laboratory	09	6
Linear Algebra I	10	10
Differential Equations I	08	10
Optics	09	12
Linear Algebra II	10	10
Differential and Integral Calculus III	07	18
Electromagnetism I	9	12
Electromagnetism Laboratory	10	6
Tensor Calculus	9	10
Differential and Integral Calculus IV	07	18
Introduction to Quantum Physics	10	12
Optics Laboratory	10	6
Thermodynamics	09	12
Advanced Mathematics of Physics	10	10
Computational Physics	10	12
Quantum Mechanics	09	12
Complex Variable I	10	10
Selected Topics of Mathematics and Theoretical Physics	10	6
Electromagnetism II	08	12
Electronics Laboratory	10	6
Statistical Physics	10	12
Contemporary Physics Laboratory I	10	6
Complex Variable II	10	10
Analytical Mechanics	10	12
Relativity	09	06
Introduction to Elementary Particle Physics I	10	06
Dynamics of Deformable Bodies	10	12
Atomic Physics and Condensed Matter	09	06
Nuclear and Subnuclear Physics	09	06
Contemporary Physics Laboratory II	10	06
Topology and Differential Geometry for Physics	10	06
Selected Topics of Relativity, Cosmology and Gravitation I	10	06
Selected Topics of Computational Physics I	10	06
English Language	AC	00
	Total Credits	418
	OVERALL SCORE	9.37